{
  "version": 2.0,
  "questions": [
    {
      "question": "1. If the magnification of objective lens and the eyepiece are 30x and 10x, the magnification that can be achieved is:",
      "answers": {
        "a": "30x",
        "b": "10x",
        "c": "3x",
        "d": "300x",
        "e": "None of the above"
      },
      "correctAnswer": "d",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "2. The role of condenser lens is:",
      "answers": {
        "a": "to protect the sample from the illumination source",
        "b": "to form a magnifying image of the specimen",
        "c": "to focus the light rays onto the specimen",
        "d": "to improve the resolution of the image",
        "e": "to partially block the rays coming from illumination source"
      },
      "correctAnswer": "c",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "3. Which objective lens will have high magnifying power",
      "answers": {
        "a": "lens with a short focal length but kept in air",
        "b": "lens with a large focal length but immersed in oil",
        "c": "lens with a large focal length but kept in air",
        "d": "lens with a short focal length but immersed in oil"
      },
      "correctAnswer": "d",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "4. If a monochromatic light of Î»=400 nm used in optical microscope having objective lens with NA of 0.8, then what would be the maximum resolution that can be achieved.",
      "answers": {
        "a": "250 nm",
        "b": "200 nm",
        "c": "25 nm",
        "d": "500 nm",
        "e": "500 nm"
      },
      "correctAnswer": "a",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "5. State which of the statement is true",
      "answers": {
        "a": "The length of the eyepiece tube is fixed",
        "b": "Microscopes are equipped with only one objective lens of a fixed magnifying power",
        "c": "Numerical aperture reduces with the increase in the focal length of the objective lens",
        "d": "High refractive index medium in which objective lens is immersed is poor to get a high-resolution image.",
        "e": "Diaphragm controls the amount of light strike the specimen."
      },
      "correctAnswer": "e",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Which part of optical microscope gather lights and focussed it on the specimen to be viewed?",
      "answers": {
        "a": "Objective lens",
        "b": "Condenser lens",
        "c": "Eyepiece lens",
        "d": "Diaphragm",
        "e": "None of the above"
      },
      "correctAnswer": "b",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Resolving power of a microscope does not depend on _________",
      "answers": {
        "a": "Wavelength of light",
        "b": "Medium in which objective lens is immersed",
        "c": "Focal length of objective lens",
        "d": "Focal length of condenser lens",
        "e": "Numerical aperture"
      },
      "correctAnswer": "d",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Total magnification of optical microscope is obtained by________",
      "answers": {
        "a": "Magnification power of objective and condenser lenses ",
        "b": "Magnification power of only condenser lens",
        "c": "Magnification power of only eyepiece",
        "d": "Magnification power of eyepiece and objective lenses",
        "e": "Magnification power of eyepiece and condenser lenses"
      },
      "correctAnswer": "d",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "9. What part of the optical microscope regulates how much light enters the viewing area?",
      "answers": {
        "a": "Condenser focus knob  ",
        "b": "Coarse adjustment knob",
        "c": "Diaphragm",
        "d": "Nosepiece",
        "e": "Diopter adjustment ring"
      },
      "correctAnswer": "c",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "10. Which component of an optical microscope will aid to achieve a clear image if an observer's eyes have some vision difference?",
      "answers": {
        "a": "Objective lens",
        "b": "Condenser lens",
        "c": "Eyepiece lens",
        "d": "Diopter adjustment ring",
        "e": "Diaphragm"
      },
      "correctAnswer": "d",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    
    {
      "question": "12. Which one of the following is not the part of the optical microscope?",
      "answers": {
        "a": "Objective lens",
        "b": "Eyepiece lens",
        "c": "Electron gun",
        "d": "Condenser lens",
        "e": "Diaphragm"
      },
      "correctAnswer": "c",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    }
  ]
}
